<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Science, meet productivity</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-11-16T11:28:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Re: “Shirtgate”</title><link href="/re-shirtgate-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-11-16T11:28:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2014-11-16:re-shirtgate-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Re &lt;a href="http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2014/11/a-pornographer-and-atheist-explains-why-the-science-guys-shirt-crash-landed/"&gt;&amp;#8220;shirtgate&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; (link is to a reasonable summary and rebuttal that I don&amp;#8217;t completely agree&amp;nbsp;with.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like it&amp;#8217;s overly simplistic to let one woman&amp;#8217;s voice stand for all women, I also think it&amp;#8217;s a jump to say that the women on this shirt represent every woman ever. I&amp;#8217;m me, and there&amp;#8217;s no other me, right? I&amp;#8217;m not on this shirt, and I don&amp;#8217;t see my career in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; melting in front of me because of this&amp;nbsp;shirt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree that this shirt says, as the linked article&amp;nbsp;claims, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every woman working on this project, every woman working on a similar project, every woman working in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt;, every woman aspiring to work in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; — this is what I think of you. Every girl dreaming of working in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; someday — this is what I’ll think of you when you’re grown up. Tits and ass. That’s what you are to&amp;nbsp;me.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shirt says, these specific women, on this shirt, are hot and surrounded by awesome sci-fi imagery. These women could be excellent scientists! Their sexiness has nothing to do with how scientifically capable they are. Maybe the models are brilliant engineers, who knows. To me, this is a very limited interpretation of the shirt, &amp;#8220;they are hot therefore they are dumb and incapable of other things,&amp;#8221; which is exactly the kind of interpretation I would like to be&amp;nbsp;combating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel offended by this shirt, that&amp;#8217;s your right and I&amp;#8217;ll fight for your right to say that. If he outright said &amp;#8220;No way women could have made this comet landing happen, they&amp;#8217;re too stupid,&amp;#8221; I would completely agree that this person is sexist. However, I personally don&amp;#8217;t feel that this choice of attire represents me at all. I&amp;#8217;m a lot more complex of a ladybeing than what&amp;#8217;s being represented on that garment, and I&amp;#8217;m not going to pretend that what someone else wore is an indication of my own&amp;nbsp;abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; agree it&amp;#8217;s an incredibly distracting shirt, a terrible fashion choice, and he needs a wardrobe upgrade. That&amp;#8217;s the kind of controversy I&amp;#8217;d stand&amp;nbsp;behind.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="social media"></category><category term="feminism"></category></entry><entry><title>Migration to Github.io!</title><link href="/migration-to-github-io-English.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-25T08:58:51-07:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2014-09-25:migration-to-github-io-English.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I moved my blog from &lt;a href="http://www.tumblr.com/"&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt; for several&amp;nbsp;reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write posts in Markdown and IPython notebooks so figures, code, and LaTeX markup would show up&amp;nbsp;fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easily back up my posts. Before, I wrote my posts in &lt;a href="http://simplenote.com/"&gt;Simplenote&lt;/a&gt; and then copy-pasted to Tumblr, but I didn&amp;#8217;t like&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t use the re-blogging or following aspects of Tumblr much so I didn&amp;#8217;t see the advantages of that&amp;nbsp;network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awesome &lt;a href="http://www.pelicanthemes.com/"&gt;customizable themes&lt;/a&gt; using&amp;nbsp;Pelican.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few drawbacks, most notably, the comments from previous posts are still tied to the Tumblr website, because Tumblr doesn&amp;#8217;t use slugs (e.g. &amp;#8220;&lt;code&gt;migration-to-github-io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;) for its webpage names, instead it uses some random number generator for keeping track of posts, e.g &amp;#8220;post/72680703972&amp;#8221;. And because &lt;a href="https://disqus.com/"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; uses the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; from the post to map it back to its database, and I couldn&amp;#8217;t get the original mapping :( So comments for old posts will be back on&amp;nbsp;Tumblr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m excited for a new start with&amp;nbsp;blogging!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="github"></category><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>The second article</title><link href="/blog/2012/12/01/the-second-article/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-12-01T10:02:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2012-12-01:blog/2012/12/01/the-second-article/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;See below intra-site link examples in Markdown&amp;nbsp;format.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>