<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Science, meet productivity - Olga Botvinnik</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/olga-botvinnik.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-12-14T12:01:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Time is Citations: How I Plan My Days</title><link href="/blog/2016/12/14/time-is-citations/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-14T12:01:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-12-14T12:01:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-12-14:/blog/2016/12/14/time-is-citations/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In business, time is money. But in academia, the currency is not published units but citations of your publications. For someone to not only read your paper but understand and cite it, you need to produce high-quality, readable papers. And that requires deep&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In business, time is money. But in academia, the currency is not published units but citations of your publications. For someone to not only read your paper but understand and cite it, you need to produce high-quality, readable papers. And that requires deep&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deep&amp;nbsp;Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m an avid reader of &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/"&gt;Cal Newport&amp;#8217;s blog&lt;/a&gt; where he writes about managing your attention and energy to output high-quality work. I strongly believe that a person&amp;#8217;s work output is directly dependent on the hours they spend in deep work. &amp;#8220;Deep work&amp;#8221; is when you are fully &amp;#8220;in the zone&amp;#8221; - you have notifications turned off on your phone, you aren&amp;#8217;t checking your email or social media, and you are fully engaged in your complex activity. For me those activities could be writing or editing a paper, adding new features to my code, carefully curating a well-designed test dataset, tweaking an explanatory figure to make it more clear, working on an upcoming presentation with a new audience, or doing a new analysis of the&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help keep track of your deep work, Cal Newport suggests &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2013/12/21/deep-habits-the-importance-of-planning-every-minute-of-your-work-day/"&gt;planning every minute of your day&lt;/a&gt;. It may sound crazy and obsessive-compulsive, but it really works. What he does is plan his day out on paper and adjust the schedule as things happen. I don&amp;#8217;t like that because then my day looks really messy and I want my &amp;#8220;on-paper&amp;#8221; plan to be an exact record of what actually happened. Instead, I plan my day out on &lt;a href="https://calendar.google.com"&gt;Google Calendar&lt;/a&gt; the day before (during the &amp;#8220;shutdown&amp;#8221; time) and record what actually happened in a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Moleskine-Daily-Planner-Large-Black/dp/B015NG44KC/ref=dp_ob_title_bk"&gt;Moleskine daily planner&lt;/a&gt; notebook (I love well made stationary products). Japanese pens are my favorite so I use the &lt;a href="http://www.jetpens.com/Uni-ball-Signo-UM-151-Gel-Pens/ct/286"&gt;Uni-ball Signo &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UM&lt;/span&gt;-151&lt;/a&gt; pens from &lt;a href="http://www.jetpens.com/blog/uni-ball-signo-a-comprehensive-guide/pt/639"&gt;JetPens&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212; my preferred color is &amp;#8220;Green Black.&amp;#8221; Additionally, I keep a &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; private GitHub repository containing markdown files for every week, and summarize what I was able to do that&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My days,&amp;nbsp;step-by-step&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the step-by-step of my planning rituals, with pointers to the columns of the figure&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/plan_vs_actual-300ppi.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Planning vs actual outcomes" src="/images/plan_vs_actual-300ppi.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the beginning of the week, I create a new markdown file and start filling it in with notes from last week and plans for this week. Sometimes my notes start with a big ole rant about some problem I&amp;#8217;ve been running into, or have a big rolling todo list that I keep updated for the week. (First column - files for each week)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The most important thing about each week&amp;#8217;s file is that each day is a separate section.&lt;/strong&gt; This way, you can keep track of the incremental progress you made that day, and what you hope to accomplish that&amp;nbsp;day. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is instead of doing project-based organization, which I find makes me less motivated because projects take a long time, so at the project-level, it doesn&amp;#8217;t look like I did much. But if I keep daily progress notes, then I feel better about&amp;nbsp;myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before each day starts, e.g. during &amp;#8220;shutdown&amp;#8221; time the day before (or sometimes on Fridays for the next Monday), I plan out what I want to do on Google Calendar. (Second column - plan for each day)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I find this works quite well because at the beginning of the day, I&amp;#8217;m bursting with energy and want to do &lt;em&gt;all of the things!&lt;/em&gt; But by the end of the day I&amp;#8217;ve realized that I can only do so much, and I&amp;#8217;m much better at prioritizing what&amp;#8217;s important, while at the beginning of the day I&amp;#8217;m much better at &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; things. So planning at the end of the day works for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I make sure to schedule 30m for &amp;#8220;shutdown&amp;#8221; at the end of the day. If I don&amp;#8217;t do this, the system breaks because I stop planning, and I am at the mercy of my morning impulses, rather than being in control of what I&amp;#8217;m trying to&amp;nbsp;do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Throughout the day, I &amp;#8220;stopwatch&amp;#8221; my time by writing down in my planner the exact minute that I start and stop each activity. (Third column)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I get interrupted, I end the time and start&amp;nbsp;again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If something comes to mind about an urgent task (e.g. submit travel insurance form), I write it down in my planner or a sticky note so I&amp;#8217;ve captured it, but continue on with my deep work. I do not interrupt my deep&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the end of the day, during &amp;#8220;shutdown,&amp;#8221; I briefly write down what I was able to do in my markdown document and what I hope to do tomorrow (Fourth&amp;nbsp;column).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally I write down the hours and minutes of deep work into the monthly part of the planner.&amp;nbsp;(below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s where I write the hours and minutes I spent in deep work each day. I find that it helps keep me motivated to sustain the work and get more hours in the next&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/deep_work_monthly_tally.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Monthly tally" src="/images/deep_work_monthly_tally.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I&amp;#8217;ve found that ~4 hours of deep work is about when I max out, because if I do 5 hours one day, next day I end up doing 2 hours. But 4 hours a day is sustainable. As you can see, December hasn&amp;#8217;t been that productive of a month for me - only about 2-3 hours of deep work a day. The 40m day was one where I was traveling and just didn&amp;#8217;t set aside a time to fully focus and was at the mercy of my&amp;nbsp;impulses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you first start doing it, you may get frustrated that you&amp;#8217;re not getting much done &amp;#8212; that&amp;#8217;s okay. I get disappointed in myself when I don&amp;#8217;t  Don&amp;#8217;t get frustrated, just keep tracking. Just like any other goal such as losing weight, results don&amp;#8217;t come right&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t overdo&amp;nbsp;it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I work in an &amp;#8220;open office&amp;#8221; environment which makes doing deep work quite difficult as there is constant movement and potential for interruptions around me. Our lab is quite collaborative so there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; times when your input or insight is needed for someone&amp;#8217;s project to go through. I made the mistake of taking this to an extreme and getting very frustrated when people would interrupt me while I was &amp;#8220;in the zone&amp;#8221; and tried to set boundaries but this closed me off from others. As Richard Hamming says in his fabulous talk, &lt;a href="http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html"&gt;You and Your Research&lt;/a&gt; about people who closed themselves&amp;nbsp;off:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I noticed the following facts about people who work with the door open or the door closed. I notice that if you have the door to your office closed, you get more work done today and tomorrow, and you are more productive than most. But 10 years later somehow you don&amp;#8217;t know quite know what problems are worth working on; all the hard work you do is sort of tangential in importance. He who works with the door open gets all kinds of interruptions, but he also occasionally gets clues as to what the world is and what might be important. Now I cannot prove the cause and effect sequence because you might say, &amp;#8220;The closed door is symbolic of a closed mind.&amp;#8221; I don&amp;#8217;t know. But I can say there is a pretty good correlation between those who work with the doors open and those who ultimately do important things, although people who work with doors closed often work harder. Somehow they seem to work on slightly the wrong thing - not much, but enough that they miss&amp;nbsp;fame.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I had to learn to temper this desire to get solid work done and strike a balance between being available and performing intense work. Now, I take lunch off to socialize and chat with the group (rather than working through it), take my headphones off when I am available to work, and when I really need to get work done, I run away and go hide in a place that nobody can find&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Take what works for&amp;nbsp;you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Productivity is very personal and what works for me may not work for you. I am not trying to say that this is the OneTrueWay(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TM&lt;/span&gt;) of being productive. This system exploits my love of &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; version control and simple Markdown text files (the &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; private github repo), beautiful writing on good paper with nice pens (hence the Moleskine planner and Japanese pens), and flexibility of Google Calendar. My system may seem overwhelming at first because it is the product of many years of trying different things. For me, online tools like Asana and Trello make planning &amp;#8220;too fun&amp;#8221; and get in the way of what I want to do. Writing &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; out on paper makes for an ugly planner with lots of crossing out which I don&amp;#8217;t like. Take the ideas that work for you and leave the ones that don&amp;#8217;t. (Thanks for the quote, &lt;a href="https://betterhumans.coach.me/do-more-of-what-already-works-e4ea4ef65b25#.3x38jsuxb!"&gt;James&amp;nbsp;Clear&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="deep-work"></category><category term="productivity"></category><category term="phd"></category><category term="grad-school"></category></entry><entry><title>IGV: Null pointer exceptions, invalid GZIP header, invalid BZIP header</title><link href="/blog/2015/05/06/igv-java-lang-nullpointerexception/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-06T15:04:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-05-06T15:04:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-05-06:/blog/2015/05/06/igv-java-lang-nullpointerexception/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve run into a &lt;code&gt;java.lang.NullPointerException&lt;/code&gt; or &amp;#8220;Invalid Gzip Header&amp;#8221; or some complaint about bzip while using the Integrative Genomics Viewer, then you&amp;#8217;ve run into the same problem as me. Turns out I had too many index (&lt;code&gt;*.bai&lt;/code&gt;) files that had similar naming to my &lt;code&gt;*.bam&lt;/code&gt; files, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IGV&lt;/span&gt; assigned the wrong ones as the index, so whenever I tried to view reads from those samples, the index pointed to the wrong location in the bam, and one of those many errors would happen. So the solution is simple (and relatively fast): use &lt;code&gt;samtools index&lt;/code&gt; on your bam&amp;nbsp;files!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve run into a &lt;code&gt;java.lang.NullPointerException&lt;/code&gt; or &amp;#8220;Invalid Gzip Header&amp;#8221; or some complaint about bzip while using the Integrative Genomics Viewer, then you&amp;#8217;ve run into the same problem as me. Turns out I had too many index (&lt;code&gt;*.bai&lt;/code&gt;) files that had similar naming to my &lt;code&gt;*.bam&lt;/code&gt; files, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IGV&lt;/span&gt; assigned the wrong ones as the index, so whenever I tried to view reads from those samples, the index pointed to the wrong location in the bam, and one of those many errors would happen. So the solution is simple (and relatively fast): use &lt;code&gt;samtools index&lt;/code&gt; on your bam&amp;nbsp;files!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="bioinformatics"></category><category term="samtools"></category><category term="igv"></category><category term="java"></category></entry><entry><title>CodeNeuro NYC 2015</title><link href="/blog/2015/04/12/codeneuro-nyc-2015/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-04-12T22:21:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-04-22T22:21:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-04-12:/blog/2015/04/12/codeneuro-nyc-2015/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I attended the &lt;a href="http://codeneuro.org/2015/NYC/"&gt;CodeNeuro &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; conference, which is a conference for neuroscientists, programmers, and everything in between. It was a unique experience because it had both the excitement and energy of a tech conference, and the pure, unadulterated zest for knowledge of a scientific&amp;nbsp;conference.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I attended the &lt;a href="http://codeneuro.org/2015/NYC/"&gt;CodeNeuro &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
conference, which is a conference for neuroscientists, programmers, and
everything in between. It was a unique experience because it had both the
excitement and energy of a tech conference, and the pure, unadulterated zest
for knowledge of a scientific&amp;nbsp;conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day 1: Talks and&amp;nbsp;panel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day of the conference started after the workday on Friday at 5pm at
the &lt;a href="http://www.newmuseum.org/"&gt;New Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Little Italy, Manhattan, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYC&lt;/span&gt;.
This was the first time I&amp;#8217;d been to this place and it was really awesome, even
from the outside! Check it out, plus some other photos I took from the&amp;nbsp;conference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" lang="en" data-id="a/q3c57"&gt;&lt;a href="//imgur.com/a/q3c57"&gt;codeneuro nyc 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FYI&lt;/span&gt; If you want to look through all the tweets from the entire event, check out this &lt;a href="https://storify.com/yangbodu/codeneuro"&gt;Storify&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;board.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference kicked off with some mingling and beer. I gravitated towards the three I knew people coming in to the conference, &lt;a href="http://www.janelia.org/people/scientist/nick-sofroniew"&gt;Nick
Sofroniew&lt;/a&gt;, with whom
I did an &lt;a href="http://www.janelia.org/student-programs/undergraduate-program#722"&gt;undergrad summer program&lt;/a&gt; and invited me to talk, &lt;a href="http://www.jeremyfreeman.net/"&gt;Jeremy Freeman&lt;/a&gt;, the main organizer of
the whole freakin&amp;#8217; thing, and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bensussman"&gt;Ben
Sussman&lt;/a&gt;, who co-taught the &lt;code&gt;gitgoing&lt;/code&gt;
tutorial with me and is an all-around awesome person. But the space was rad,
we had a balcony and a nice view of the city, and I got to meet a bunch of
people doing super interesting things in&amp;nbsp;neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;view from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CodeNeuro"&gt;@CodeNeuro&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8230; &lt;a href="http://t.co/kInTbaFWHW"&gt;pic.twitter.com/kInTbaFWHW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Angela Radulescu (@angitweets) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/angitweets/status/586659812198522880"&gt;April 10, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got started with the talks, which we had three 10 minute (ish) talks, followed by a half hour (ish) break. It was a nice format that we could chat and break in between the talks not only to get a mental break but also discuss the concepts presented by the previous talks in the context of neuroscience. Here&amp;#8217;s all the&amp;nbsp;talks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adam Packer (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCL&lt;/span&gt;): All optical recording and manipulation of individual&amp;nbsp;neurons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eiman Azim (Columbia): Quantitative behavior and mouse genetics for probing motor circuit&amp;nbsp;function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Randal Burns (Johns Hopkins): Open Connectome project using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CATMAID&lt;/span&gt; [&lt;a href="https://github.com/openconnectome/ocpcatmaid"&gt;github repo&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paco Nathan (Databricks): Spark for big&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eliza Chang (The Data Incubator): PhD to Data&amp;nbsp;Scientist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Dewar (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYT&lt;/span&gt;): Real-time analytics on streaming data [&lt;a href="https://github.com/mikedewar/codeneuro_streamtools"&gt;github repo for presentation&lt;/a&gt;] | [&lt;a href="https://github.com/nytlabs/streamtools"&gt;github repo for &lt;code&gt;streamtools&lt;/code&gt; package&lt;/a&gt;] &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hilary Parker (Etsy): Data science at Etsy (+&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CodeNeuro/status/586696965502689280"&gt;cute statistical plushies&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brendan Lake (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYU&lt;/span&gt;): Teaching computers to scribble characters like&amp;nbsp;humans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Olga Botvinnik, me! (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCSD&lt;/span&gt;): &lt;code&gt;flotilla&lt;/code&gt;: An open-source Python package for iterative machine learning analyses [&lt;a href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/format/slides/gist/olgabot/2ee1087d74df46c842df#/"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine from the caliber of all the other talks, I was super nervous for mine! because I&amp;#8217;m not doing things at exabyte scale, I&amp;#8217;m not doing streaming data, and I&amp;#8217;m not even doing neuroscience! I&amp;#8217;m just analyzing static datasets with the usual machine learning algorithms. But as Jeremy pointed out, we need better tools for analyzing the existing non-big data datasets that we have, plus I got great questions and feedback from the talk which was&amp;nbsp;great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My top three favorite talks&amp;nbsp;were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NYT&lt;/span&gt; R&amp;amp;D demo&lt;/strong&gt; This was a fantastic talk about streaming data analytics.  He
and his team had created an interactive way to analyze real-time data. They
had a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt; interface where you could select boxes that represented an action on
data (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extract,_transform,_load"&gt;extract, transform, load aka
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ETL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-like things), and
you could string these boxes together to create an analysis pipeline. It
reminded me a lot of the &lt;a href="https://usegalaxy.org/"&gt;Galaxy&lt;/a&gt; interface for
reproducible bioinformatics pipelines. Check out the tweet below for a&amp;nbsp;screenshot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Picture of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/realTimeData?src=hash"&gt;#realTimeData&lt;/a&gt; including mine &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/codeNeuro?src=hash"&gt;#codeNeuro&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://t.co/VCIfFlFHTK"&gt;pic.twitter.com/VCIfFlFHTK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; aybuke turker (@aybuketurker) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/aybuketurker/status/586678871942111232"&gt;April 10, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optogenetics&lt;/strong&gt;. This was a really interesting talk about &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics"&gt;optogenetics&lt;/a&gt;, which is a way that you can control the brain with light. Researchers genetically insert &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhodopsin"&gt;rhodopsin&lt;/a&gt;, which is the light-sensitive protein that makes our eyes work, into neurons, which then makes them light sensitive. As a result, you can then turn specific neurons on and off with light! This talk used both this tool of optogenetics to stimulate/inhibit specific neurons, and calcium imaging to record their&amp;nbsp;responses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A. Packer shows some amazing tools to simultaneously record + stimulate ensembles of neurons with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/CaImaging?src=hash"&gt;#CaImaging&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/optogenetics?src=hash"&gt;#optogenetics&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/codeneuro?src=hash"&gt;#codeneuro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Felipe Gerhard (@neuroflips) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/neuroflips/status/586685623068717056"&gt;April 11, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spark&lt;/strong&gt;. This was an awesome talk by &lt;a href="http://liber118.com/pxn/"&gt;Paco Nathan&lt;/a&gt;
on using big data tools. Paco had worked with both Hadoop and Spark and gave a
great overview of the history of Big Data (which he pinpointed to Q3 1997),
the different papers about it and tools for it, and where Spark fits in that
ecosystem. He gave a few use cases and was overall just a very entertaining&amp;nbsp;presenter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Great talk by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/placoid"&gt;@placoid&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CodeNeuro"&gt;@CodeNeuro&lt;/a&gt; just now - apparently rotational bearings on planes create 12 exabytes of data / day&amp;#8230; wow &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bigdata?src=hash"&gt;#bigdata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alice Lloyd George (@&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AMLG23&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AMLG23/status/586689726196883458"&gt;April 11, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all the talks, there was a panel led by Jeremy with some giants of
neuroscientists, Tony Movshon, Eve Marder and Larry Abbott. A recurring theme
was that the fundamental questions of how the brain works hasn&amp;#8217;t changed, but
the tools have drastically&amp;nbsp;changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One story that stuck with me was Eve describing that when she was doing
experiments, she used an
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oscilloscope"&gt;oscilloscope&lt;/a&gt; to listen (yes, with
her ears! I thought this was amazing!) to the measurements from neurons, and
there was a direct, phsyical, visceral reaction that when you designed an
experiment and heard specific tones, you knew &lt;strong&gt;exactly&lt;/strong&gt; what that meant,
because you were intimately familiar with the exact tones and sounds produced
by the device. But now, she said, the high throughput methods, while capable
of measuring many things at once, are so detached from the physicality of
neurons firing that she feels people aren&amp;#8217;t connected to what they&amp;#8217;re
measuring anymore. I found that interesting because in my field of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RNA&lt;/span&gt;
biology, we&amp;#8217;ll do these newfangled &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA_sequencing#Next-
generation_methods"&gt;high-throughput sequencing
experiments&lt;/a&gt; to measure &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RNA&lt;/span&gt; expression as a proxy for protein
abundance, and study the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alternative_splicing"&gt;alternative
splicing&lt;/a&gt; of these &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RNA&lt;/span&gt;
transcripts, but every time, we always have to validate our findings using an
older, low-throughput method like &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revers
e_transcription_polymerase_chain_reaction"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RT&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PCR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;#8217;t know what the equivalent
experiments are in neuroscience, because it seems all very magical to me that
they&amp;#8217;re able to manipulate individual neurons in mice, but I also wonder if
it&amp;#8217;s known that the neuron in the exact same position in one animal and
another animal, do the exact same thing. So far, biology has relied on laws of
averages, so if you do a high throughput experiment on a bunch of cells and
get an average signal, you should get that same result if you do a low-
throughput version of that experiment. I don&amp;#8217;t know what the equivalent of
that is in neuroscience, but it was refreshing to hear that neuro has its own
share of growing pains as its adopted its own high-throughput techniques, and
that biology wasn&amp;#8217;t the only&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to hear about the challenges of neuroscience, of how
excited people are about optogenetics, and how many people are apparently
skeptical of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_magnetic_resonance_imaging"&gt;functional magentic resonance
imaging&lt;/a&gt;
(fMRI) data, and how nobody knows what the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cerebral_cortex"&gt;cerebral
cortex&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;does!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day 2: Tutorials +&amp;nbsp;Hackathon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning we were in the &lt;a href="http://www.newinc.org/"&gt;New, Inc&lt;/a&gt; coworking
space, and started off with some kickass bagels and&amp;nbsp;lox/salmon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;breakfast begins &lt;a href="http://t.co/55QljXZqkw"&gt;pic.twitter.com/55QljXZqkw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; CodeNeuro (@CodeNeuro) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CodeNeuro/status/586893786212651008"&gt;April 11, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, people split up about 50/50 for the tutorials and the&amp;nbsp;hackathon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;gitgoing&lt;/code&gt; tutorial&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben Sussman and I taught a tutorial called
&lt;a href="https://github.com/CodeNeuro/gitgoing"&gt;gitgoing&lt;/a&gt; to quickly teach scientists
the version control system
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Git_%28software%29"&gt;&lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and code testing via
&lt;a href="http://pytest.org/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;py.test&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and integration systems via &lt;a href="https://travis-ci.org/"&gt;Travis-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We had about 20-30 attendees. The goal was to get the
scientists acquainted with common tools in open source software so that they
could contribute themselves. It was kind of like a mini &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software
Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; workshop, but we assumed our target
audience had some coding experience, and we didn&amp;#8217;t take the time to explain
computer science fundamentals like variables, loops, flow control,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our class was structured exactly as laid out in the &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; file. First we
setup their computers so they had &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; and Python 2.7. This took about an hour
total to get everyone done. Some people finished faster and started moving on to
the &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; section. Then Ben did an awesome explanation of &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, and I learned a
bunch of stuff! I didn&amp;#8217;t realize that when you &lt;code&gt;git clone&lt;/code&gt; a repo, you&amp;#8217;re
getting &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ENTIRE&lt;/span&gt; history of the project, so that makes sense why downloading all
of &lt;a href="ipython.org"&gt;IPython&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://jupyter.org/"&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; takes forever. It was
also a really helpful analogy to describe the entire repository as an &amp;#8220;ocean of
code,&amp;#8221; and that a branch is a single window into that ocean. We also talked
about merge conflicts, and how they can be really easy to create if, say someone
renamed one of the arguments of a function, and someone else added an argument,
and then &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; doesn&amp;#8217;t know what to do anymore. They picked up on testing pretty
quickly, and someone asked &amp;#8220;well &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; thinks it&amp;#8217;s okay, but how do you know
the code will run?&amp;#8221; Which brought us directly to&amp;nbsp;testing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I talked about testing and why it&amp;#8217;s important. I wrote some simple Python
code with functions like &lt;code&gt;mean_plus_one&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;std_plus_one&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;cv&lt;/code&gt; (coefficient
of variance). They were just slight variations on the true
&lt;a href="http://www.numpy.org/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; functions so the learners couldn&amp;#8217;t just use the
&lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; version. We looked at the test file, &lt;code&gt;test_gitgoing.py&lt;/code&gt; which used
&lt;code&gt;py.test&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;&amp;#8216;&lt;/span&gt;s fixtures, which take care of the &lt;code&gt;setUp&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;tearDown&lt;/code&gt; methods that
some other testing frameworks have. We saw a simple example of fixtures, which
creates a 20x10 matrix of normally distributed random numbers. These could have
been set as integers, I just wanted to illustrate how you can create new
fixtures from existing&amp;nbsp;ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pytest&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nd"&gt;@pytest.fixture&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;n_rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nd"&gt;@pytest.fixture&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;n_cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nd"&gt;@pytest.fixture&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;x_norm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;n_rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;n_cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;randn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;n_rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;n_cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a commented out broken test in the repo which they had to fix, which was a great formative assessment because they had to use their newly formed &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; and testing knowledge to fix the test, commit the changes, make a branch of their &amp;#8220;feature&amp;#8221; fixing the test, pushing to the branch, and making a pull request to the master branch. It was really rewarding for the students to see their pull request on Github, and to see their commits on the network of contributors to the &lt;code&gt;gitgoing&lt;/code&gt; repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We unfortunately didn&amp;#8217;t advertise the #gitgoing hashtag before the tutorial so we didn&amp;#8217;t get any live-tweets, but Ben and I mitigated this and took a picture&amp;nbsp;afterwards:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/gitgoing?src=hash"&gt;#gitgoing&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CodeNeuro"&gt;@CodeNeuro&lt;/a&gt;! Thanks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bensussman"&gt;@bensussman&lt;/a&gt; for being an awesome co-teacher and everyone for coming! &lt;a href="http://t.co/l0BUhoeWja"&gt;pic.twitter.com/l0BUhoeWja&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Olga Botvinnik (@olgabot) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/olgabot/status/586980895397019650"&gt;April 11, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Spark&amp;nbsp;tutorial&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;code&gt;gitgoing&lt;/code&gt; tutorial we had a break and mingled. Then, I went to the Spark tutorial, taught by &lt;a href="http://liber118.com/pxn/"&gt;Paco Nathan&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://databricks.com/"&gt;DataBricks&lt;/a&gt; (slides &lt;a href="http://training.databricks.com/workshop/dbc_intro.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I&amp;#8217;ve seen Spark demos before but I haven&amp;#8217;t put in the time to play around with the tools, so this was a great way to get&amp;nbsp;exposed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a little late to the tutorial, so I missed the initial setup. I was handed a slip of paper with a url, username and password that was my personal login to the DataBricks cloud. Paco was doing a &amp;#8220;preflight check&amp;#8221; of explaining different Spark concepts before we dove in. The key things I took away&amp;nbsp;were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RDD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Resilient Distributed Dataset. This is the core unit of a spark analysis, where you load in data, and use Spark to indicate that you want it to be&amp;nbsp;parallelized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;sc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;#8220;Spark context.&amp;#8221; This is the object that exists in all the Python library versions with Spark, and is the object that you will be using to create and operate on&amp;nbsp;datasets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used an IPython notebook-style &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;REPL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; interface, which was really nice because we could see the output from our commands right away. We continued with learning how&amp;nbsp;to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read text files and separate lines by&amp;nbsp;tabs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filter for the first word of the line to be &lt;code&gt;ERROR&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get all the second words of the error&amp;nbsp;lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the errors that were caused by &lt;code&gt;"mysql"&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see a summary of my notes for this first section&amp;nbsp;here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lines&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;textFile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;/mnt/paco/intro/error_log.txt&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; \
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;errors&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;lines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;ERROR&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;messages&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;errors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;messages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;find&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;mysql&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# At this point, the data is loaded into memory on the workers and you don&amp;#39;t&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# need to attack disk again, so this operation is very fast&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;messages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;find&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;php&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yay, we learned how to read files! Always good&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next part of the tutorial, we learned how to use &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt;, and then how to &lt;code&gt;join&lt;/code&gt; several RDDs on their &lt;code&gt;(key, value)&lt;/code&gt; pairs. After the break, we had a mini lecture about &amp;#8220;Computational thinking&amp;#8221; where we had to use what we learned so far to find all the instances of the word &amp;#8220;Spark&amp;#8221; in two files. If you&amp;#8217;re interested, you can see my full notes &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/olgabot/ab058876b3bda6198f25"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hackathon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hackathon was centered around the &lt;a href="http://codeneuro.org/neurofinder/"&gt;neurofinder&lt;/a&gt; challenge, which is to try and extract neuronal signals from Calcium imaging data. The goals were&amp;nbsp;go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refine a standardized &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; for &amp;#8220;source extraction&amp;#8221; algorithms, including input/ouptut&amp;nbsp;formats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on evaluation metrics for algorithms and agree on ground truth&amp;nbsp;definition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on incorporating existing algorithms into this &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on the frontend/backend of a website that would automatically run submitted algorithms on the test data, get the results and upload them to a&amp;nbsp;leaderboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, everyone introduced themselves and the group organically split into a few groups: the website, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; input/output formatting, implementing algorithms, and designing&amp;nbsp;metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The website team was composed of five people with web development frontend/backend experience. They generated some prototype websites and code, all available on &lt;a href="https://github.com/codeneuro/neurofinder"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;, and hopefully launching in beta&amp;nbsp;soon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another group of about 25 worked on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; and the input/output formats, with their final notes added to &lt;a href="https://github.com/CodeNeuro/neurofinder/wiki"&gt;this wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another group of 10-20 split to work on incorporating existing algorithms in to this &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;. The rest worked on defining evaluation metrics for algorithms and the &amp;#8220;ground truth&amp;#8221; definitions of &amp;#8220;what is a neuron&amp;#8221; for these methods. They implemented some evaluation metrics, and developed an initial ground truth definition of manual centers and morphological boundaries. They discussed that this initial &amp;#8220;ground truth&amp;#8221; risks circularity, but is still a solid&amp;nbsp;start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were still people working well into the&amp;nbsp;evening!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;the codeneuro hardcore, still rocking! &lt;a href="http://t.co/TyxmlSNOZB"&gt;pic.twitter.com/TyxmlSNOZB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; CodeNeuro (@CodeNeuro) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CodeNeuro/status/587072775057231872"&gt;April 12, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, we all hung out at a nice&amp;nbsp;dinner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="CodeNeuro after-dinner party" src="http://i.imgur.com/KY9smQR.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to acknowledge all the organizers of the&amp;nbsp;event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jeremyfreeman.net"&gt;Jeremy&amp;nbsp;Freeman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/neuro_nick"&gt;Nick&amp;nbsp;Sofroniew&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://graphics.stanford.edu/~broxton/"&gt;Michael&amp;nbsp;Broxton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mathisonian.com/"&gt;Matt&amp;nbsp;Conlen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.stanford.edu/~logang/"&gt;Logan&amp;nbsp;Grosenick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dgangul1"&gt;Deep&amp;nbsp;Ganguli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hackingdata"&gt;Jeff&amp;nbsp;Hammerbacher&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="programming"></category><category term="conferences"></category><category term="bioinformatics"></category><category term="neuroscience"></category></entry><entry><title>Things said to me</title><link href="/blog/2015/04/07/things-said-to-me/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-04-07T11:17:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-04-07T11:17:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-04-07:/blog/2015/04/07/things-said-to-me/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I read the &lt;a href="http://the-toast.net/2015/04/01/things-male-tech-colleagues-have-actually-said-annotated/"&gt;things my male tech colleagues have said to me&lt;/a&gt; article and thought about my own experience. Thankfully I haven&amp;#8217;t been subjected to nearly as many microagressions (but hey I&amp;#8217;m still young! there&amp;#8217;s plenty of time!), but there were a few points that resonated wih&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Too long for a tweet, too short for a proper blog post, but going in here&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read the &lt;a href="http://the-toast.net/2015/04/01/things-male-tech-colleagues-have-actually-said-annotated/"&gt;things my male tech colleagues have said to me&lt;/a&gt; article and thought about my own experience. Thankfully I haven&amp;#8217;t been subjected to nearly as many microagressions (but hey I&amp;#8217;m still young! there&amp;#8217;s plenty of time!), but there were a few points that resonated wih&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;You don&amp;#8217;t look like you&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#8220;Most girls aren&amp;#8217;t &amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;&lt;/strong&gt;* Boston is a melting pot of colleges and you&amp;#8217;ll often start conversations at parties with, &amp;#8220;What school do you go to?&amp;#8221; I got tired of hearing &amp;#8220;You don&amp;#8217;t look like you {go to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt;, major in math/eng}&amp;#8221; when guys asked me this at parties in college, so my friend and I started to respond with &amp;#8220;guess&amp;#8221; when asked, and they were usually taken aback. They&amp;#8217;d say &amp;#8220;Well only &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt; girls would say that, so you must go to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;#8221; At least I turned it around on&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting mixed up with receptionists.&lt;/strong&gt; First of all, being a receptionist/administrative assistant is a difficult and thankless job. You are constantly behind the scenes making sure everything is running smoothly and taking care of all kinds of tasks that nobody else wants to do. It&amp;#8217;s hard work. That said, it&amp;#8217;s unfortunate that these positions are seen as low-skill and as such, only for eye-candy women who aren&amp;#8217;t good for anything else. I&amp;#8217;m not a receptionist, and you should respect (not assume) my career choices as well as the&amp;nbsp;receptionist&amp;#8217;s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="tech"></category><category term="feminism"></category></entry><entry><title>2014 Annual Review</title><link href="/blog/2015/02/22/2014-annual-review/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-22T13:29:35-08:00</published><updated>2015-02-22T13:29:35-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-02-22:/blog/2015/02/22/2014-annual-review/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I subscribed to &lt;a href="http://jamesclear.com/"&gt;James Clear&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s blog and his writing and advice has resonated with me. The last time I felt like someone was speaking directly through me was Cal Newport&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/"&gt;Study Hacks&lt;/a&gt; blog, which I discovered during undergrad, and I felt it directly addressed the issues I was having with keeping up with my intense courseload. James Clear posted his &lt;a href="http://jamesclear.com/2014-annual-review"&gt;2014 Annual Review&lt;/a&gt; in December, and it reminded me of how we do annual self-evaluations for work. I read through my evaluation for 2013 and enjoyed reflecting back on that time, how much I did then, what didn&amp;#8217;t go well, and what I&amp;#8217;ve learned since. So I&amp;#8217;m going to follow his template with the following three questions: 1. What went well this year? 2. What didn&amp;#8217;t go so well this year? 3. What am I working&amp;nbsp;toward?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I subscribed to &lt;a href="http://jamesclear.com/"&gt;James Clear&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s blog and his writing and advice has resonated with me. The last time I felt like someone was speaking directly through me was Cal Newport&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/"&gt;Study Hacks&lt;/a&gt; blog, which I discovered during undergrad, and I felt it directly addressed the issues I was having with keeping up with my intense&amp;nbsp;courseload. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Clear posted his &lt;a href="http://jamesclear.com/2014-annual-review"&gt;2014 Annual Review&lt;/a&gt; in December, and it reminded me of how we do annual self-evaluations for work. I read through my evaluation for 2013 and enjoyed reflecting back on that time, how much I did then, what didn&amp;#8217;t go well, and what I&amp;#8217;ve learned since. So I&amp;#8217;m going to follow his template with the following three&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What went well this&amp;nbsp;year?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What didn’t go so well this&amp;nbsp;year?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What am I working&amp;nbsp;toward?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. What went well this&amp;nbsp;year?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellowships.&lt;/strong&gt; This year, I was the first and sole recipient of the &lt;a href="http://numfocus.org/news/2014/07/01/john-hunter-technology-fellowship-awarded/"&gt;NumFOCUS John Hunter Technology Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;. I was thrilled to receive it, especially because I thought I had no chance of getting it. From the wording of the announcement, which said &amp;#8220;postdoctoral scientists or senior graduate students,&amp;#8221; I thought I wasn&amp;#8217;t seasoned enough, and I figured people who work on &lt;a href="http://scikit-learn.org/stable/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;IPython&lt;/a&gt; would apply and definitely get it over me. Plus I couldn&amp;#8217;t think of anyone who would be willing to be my Software Mentor, as required for the application. Thankfully, at &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2014/"&gt;PyCon&lt;/a&gt;, I was talking to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ctitusbrown"&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt; and mentioned that I wanted to apply to this fellowship but thought I wouldn&amp;#8217;t get it, and that didn&amp;#8217;t have a Software Mentor. Immediately, he dismissed my doubts and offered be my Software Mentor, on the spot! I almost cried because I was so happy and surprised to hear someone believe in me so strongly, especially because for the previous year I had been getting major shade and negativity from certain peers back home, which majorly impacted my mental state and made me feel constantly&amp;nbsp;inadequate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python involvement.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#8217;m very proud to have contributed to the &lt;a href="http://web.stanford.edu/~mwaskom/software/seaborn/index.html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; statistical data visualization Python package, specifically creating the first-ever (that I know of) single-line clustered heatmap function in Python! It was months of work, and couldn&amp;#8217;t have been done without the input from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mike_t_lovci"&gt;Mike Lovci&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cdeboever3"&gt;Christopher DeBoever&lt;/a&gt;. Plus now I have more clout to evangelize Python for bioinformatics research&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passed Qualifying Exam!&lt;/strong&gt; On May 15th, 2014, I proved my competency to a group of three professors, who all agreed that I can move on to the next stage of graduate school! I spent a solid month writing and working on my presentation and was &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; nervous and stressed about it, so it was very satisfying to be&amp;nbsp;over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Travel and conferences&lt;/strong&gt; Last year I traveled&amp;nbsp;to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strata 2014 in Santa Clara,&amp;nbsp;California&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyCon 2014 in Montreal,&amp;nbsp;Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-quals vacation in Cabo San Lucas,&amp;nbsp;Mexico&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single-cell genomics conference in Stockholm, Sweden. Plus Italy (Rome and Venice)&amp;nbsp;afterwards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyData 2014 (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IQksDvFl2_8"&gt;gave a talk!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a great experience to visit these places and make new friends in the Python, data science, and single-cell communities. Looking forward to more this&amp;nbsp;year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photography&lt;/strong&gt; While I haven&amp;#8217;t publicly shared much photography, I&amp;#8217;ve taken lots of photos on these different trips. The Europe trip was especially good, because I purposely tested out different settings in low light and other tough situations, and I spent a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOT&lt;/span&gt; of time watching LightRoom tutorials on editing, and learned a lot of new techniques that I&amp;#8217;ve been practicing with new&amp;nbsp;photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal relationships.&lt;/strong&gt; I had some tough interpersonal issues this year and in talking through it with a friend, they recommended the book &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Difficult-Conversations-Discuss-What-Matters/dp/0143118447"&gt;Difficult Conversations&lt;/a&gt;. I highly recommend this book to everyone, because difficult conversations happen every day, and this will provide you the tools and perspectives you need to understand them. I can honestly say that the book has changed my life and helped me critically evaluate everyone&amp;#8217;s role in a tricky spot, and come up with strategies in how to approach these situations tactfully. Tact has never been my strong suit, so these lessons were&amp;nbsp;eye-opening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. What didn&amp;#8217;t go so well this&amp;nbsp;year?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not being afraid of the unknown or difficult.&lt;/strong&gt; These first few years of graduate school, if some task took steps that I couldn&amp;#8217;t clearly visualize, or I could see them but I thought they were too hard, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t do it, and my research would suffer as a result. For example, I&amp;#8217;ve been putting off doing a complicated operation on a bunch of sequences that would help my research in ways I can&amp;#8217;t comprehend now, but it was so nebulous to me that I didn&amp;#8217;t even want to attempt it. Or I&amp;#8217;d get some result and not know how to interpret it, and the solution was to go to the literature and read a bunch of papers about those genes, but that&amp;#8217;s too hard so I didn&amp;#8217;t want to do&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blogging.&lt;/strong&gt; I published 10 total blog posts in 2014. I switched to hosting my blog using github.io rather than Tumblr in 2014. I thought my lack of blogging was a result of my blog being on Tumblr and being ugly and annoying to write IPython notebook style blog posts for it, rather than using markdown/IPython entries. I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; have 6 blog posts after September, compared to 4 pre-September, so the change helped. But I still feel I could have blogged more, even small random things I found helpful like that bit about using &lt;a href="http://blog.olgabotvinnik.com/different-branches-different-ipython-notebooks-.html"&gt;different git branches in different IPython notebooks&lt;/a&gt;, which was a great discovery for me in my development workflow. I think part of my lack of posts was also the misguided belief that every post has to be a gigantic, perfectly crafted tome, when it&amp;#8217;s fine to have a concise 100-word&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publishing.&lt;/strong&gt; I didn&amp;#8217;t complete any scientific publications this year. While it&amp;#8217;s not common for a 2nd-year graduate student to publish a paper, I thought I was working hard towards that goal, but in reality, I didn&amp;#8217;t understand the magnitude of work that goes into a publication. I also think my &lt;em&gt;being afraid of the unknown&lt;/em&gt;, not knowing how to do something and being afraid of being wrong, also played into&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular progress reviews.&lt;/strong&gt; Every once in a while I put together weekly progress reviews of what I did that week and what&amp;#8217;s the plan for the next week. It makes me feel good, and it works for a bit, but then I give it up because I think &amp;#8220;ehh, I&amp;#8217;ll just remember what I need to do.&amp;#8221; I feel I spend too much time on trivial things like reformatting code or making some plot look just slightly better (but not necessarily more readable), rather than moving on to the next&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python involvement.&lt;/strong&gt; You may wonder why this topic is in both the &amp;#8220;went well&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;didn&amp;#8217;t go so well&amp;#8221; categories. While I&amp;#8217;m happy with my &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt; contributions, I haven&amp;#8217;t been as happy with other things. There&amp;#8217;s been features I&amp;#8217;ve wanted to add to &lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (read gzipped files over the internet) and other visualization features to &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;, I haven&amp;#8217;t gotten around to doing them. I did start subscribing to &lt;code&gt;matplotlib-devel&lt;/code&gt; and watching the &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt; repo for all issues, and replied to a few, but I&amp;#8217;m still afraid that I don&amp;#8217;t have anything to add to the&amp;nbsp;conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sustaining interest.&lt;/strong&gt; As both &lt;a href="http://jamesclear.com/stay-focused"&gt;James Clear&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2009/06/22/on-the-value-of-hard-focus/"&gt;Cal Newport&lt;/a&gt; have discussed, it&amp;#8217;s consistent, sustained effort and focus over a long period of time which generates results. I find it really easy to start something fresh and new, and I struggle with maintaining interest in something long enough to reap the rewards at the&amp;nbsp;end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cello&lt;/strong&gt; Last January I performed a small cello concert for my friends, and worked really hard practicing a lot for it. But this last six months I haven&amp;#8217;t practiced much. Part of it is my teacher had personal commitments that prevented him from teaching for some time, but I think the more major part is that I didn&amp;#8217;t pay for my lessons. I was supposed to help him with his &lt;a href="http://www.celloloftmusic.com/cellosophy/"&gt;Cellosophy&lt;/a&gt; cello app, but honestly I just bit off more than I could chew. The coding was going to be for the instructor website in &lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3.js&lt;/a&gt; and that&amp;#8217;s not part of my core competency, so it was a lot of work for me to just make a bar chart. And so I didn&amp;#8217;t do a good job of collaborating&amp;#8230; and as a result I didn&amp;#8217;t ascribe as much value as I should have to my lessons, and didn&amp;#8217;t invest as much time in them. Once I get back into cello, I&amp;#8217;m going to pay for them. As expensive as they are, they are worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fitness&lt;/strong&gt; I was very good about going to yoga and exercising 4+ times a week, but something happened around August and I stopped working out as much. I gained some weight and lost fitness, and I&amp;#8217;m now trying to change that (see next&amp;nbsp;section).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. What am I working&amp;nbsp;toward?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular progress reviews + Time-boxing.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve started &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2013/12/21/deep-habits-the-importance-of-planning-every-minute-of-your-work-day/"&gt;planning my workday&lt;/a&gt; carefully in a &lt;a href="http://amzn.com/8867322729?tag=sciencmeetpro-20"&gt;Moleskine daily planner&lt;/a&gt; (in green, my favorite color). This is part of what my colleague &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/leenyann"&gt;Colleen Stoyas&lt;/a&gt; likes to call &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/LeenyAnn/status/563335731070771200"&gt;#projectGETONYOGAME&lt;/a&gt;. Writing down how I spend my hours has been a very effective way for me to keep track of where the time goes, especially when it turns out that what I thought was a 30 minute break turned into an hour and a half of eating and chatting&amp;#8230; yikes. I&amp;#8217;m taking the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1585425524/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1585425524&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=sciencmeetpro-20&amp;amp;linkId=PJBK7XP4R2HJIX6N"&gt;Now Habit&lt;/a&gt; approach of not trying to change my habits dramatically, but writing everything down and paying attention to what I&amp;#8217;m doing. Below are some example schedules I&amp;#8217;ve created, for days that went as planned, and others that did not. The images have been blurred for&amp;nbsp;privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a sample day that went quite well, and I mostly stuck to my schedule. You&amp;#8217;ll notice I have some random notes on the side of reminders of people to meet with, and I even drew out a network. However, I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; end up taking a 1.5 hour break from lingering around and chatting, which I probably could have shortened and ended my day&amp;nbsp;earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://imgur.com/3FbYHIa"&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/3FbYHIa.jpg" alt="Example hour plan for a day that went mostly as planned" style="width: 200px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is an example day that didn&amp;#8217;t go as planned, where I started late and thus deviated from the schedule quite a bit. I also got the time wrong for when I was supposed to be teaching data cleaning (2pm not 12pm), so that changed things up too. While this didn&amp;#8217;t go completely as planned, I was able to squeeze a lot of work&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://imgur.com/iNcLFjg"&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/iNcLFjg.jpg" alt="Example hour plan for a day that didn't go as planned" style="width: 200px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publishing.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;#8217;s hard for me to call a project &amp;#8220;done enough,&amp;#8221; and yet this is exactly what I need to do to be able to publish. I have a couple conference abstract and presentation deadlines coming up in the next few months which will help me to focus on creating &amp;#8220;publishable units.&amp;#8221; Plus I have my advancement in a month, so that will be a big push to get manuscripts ready so I can say that certain projects are at least &amp;#8220;submitted&amp;#8221; to my&amp;nbsp;committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://grad.ucsd.edu/progress/candidacy.html"&gt;Advancing to candidacy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; In our program, the &amp;#8220;Advancement Exam&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Senate Exam&amp;#8221; is when you show your committee what research you&amp;#8217;ve accomplished so far, and your plan for your PhD. I&amp;#8217;m very nervous for it, and have been doing a lot of background reading to be able to motivate why my projects are important, and why they make sense to be done together. I&amp;#8217;m planning to do this in March, so wish me&amp;nbsp;luck!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fitness.&lt;/strong&gt; I signed up for my first half-marathon, the &lt;a href="http://www.lajollahalfmarathon.com/"&gt;La Jolla Half Marathon&lt;/a&gt;! I&amp;#8217;ve been training hard for it, maybe a little too hard because I hurt my knee and am resting it now (no running for 1&amp;nbsp;week!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photography.&lt;/strong&gt; I have a bunch of photos I&amp;#8217;ve taken of nature, flowers, architecture, scenery, and LegoLand that I use as backgrounds, and I&amp;#8217;m planning on sharing them as an album. As motivation, I&amp;#8217;m also planning to apply to this year&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2014/09/ubuntu-14-10-wallpaper-contest-winners"&gt;Ubuntu Wallpaper Contest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cello.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#8217;m going to start scheduling time to play cello, even if its only fifteen minutes, it&amp;#8217;s still an important&amp;nbsp;investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="review"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="professional"></category><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Teaching “Data cleaning”</title><link href="/blog/2015/01/29/teaching-data-cleaning/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-01-29T13:51:43-08:00</published><updated>2015-01-29T13:51:43-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-01-29:/blog/2015/01/29/teaching-data-cleaning/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our compute cluster is down for maintenance, so obviously instead of working on my advancement exam presentation, I&amp;#8217;m gonna write a blog post about teaching &amp;#8220;data cleaning&amp;#8221; to graduate students in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCSD&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BIOM&lt;/span&gt; 262: &amp;#8220;Quantitative Methods in Genetics&amp;#8221; class, where I taught &lt;a href="http://www.python.org/"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;IPython Notebook&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; techniques for teaching technical&amp;nbsp;skills.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our compute cluster is down for maintenance, so obviously instead of working on my advancement exam presentation, I&amp;#8217;m gonna write a blog&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I taught a 1-hour lesson on &amp;#8220;Cleaning data&amp;#8221; for graduate students in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCSD&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BIOM262&lt;/span&gt;: Quantitative Methods in Genetics class. Here is the &lt;a href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/gist/olgabot/edebccd736d051d8a1c7"&gt;IPython notebook&lt;/a&gt; that I used. While designing the lesson, I used concepts I learned from &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s &lt;a href="http://teaching.software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Training for instructors&lt;/a&gt;, such&amp;nbsp;as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing the lesson incrementally, so every step builds upon&amp;nbsp;itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When designing a lesson, have the final task in mind and teach to&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being as clear as possible for each&amp;nbsp;step&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the workshop, I again implemented things we learned in software carpentry, such as working in pairs and using stickie notes to indicate progress. Overall, I thought it went quite well, with students being engaged for most of the time. Here&amp;#8217;s the results of what went well and what could be&amp;nbsp;improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the things I thought went&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everyone worked in pairs&lt;/strong&gt;. Before we split into pairs, I surveyed the class to check for previous experience with &lt;a href="http://www.python.org/"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;IPython Notebook&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt;. Then, the person who has &lt;strong&gt;less&lt;/strong&gt; experience was the one who did all the typing (aka &amp;#8220;driving&amp;#8221; in pair-programming parlance), and the more experienced person wasn&amp;#8217;t allowed to type. We did this at the software carpentry training while doing a &lt;a href="https://github.com/"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; exercise. I paired with someone who was less experienced with Github, and it was a good experience for me to have to sit on my hands and talk through every step. This was very useful because the more experienced person had to be explicit and describe every step, and the less experienced person automatically had a mentor to ask &amp;#8220;dumb&amp;#8221; questions to, without having to grab an instructor. An additional benefit is that when working in pairs, you&amp;#8217;re held more accountable, so you can&amp;#8217;t just do some exercises and then switch to your email or facebook, because your partner is right&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Used pink and blue stickies to show progress.&lt;/strong&gt; Pink was &amp;#8220;still working&amp;#8221; and blue was &amp;#8220;done.&amp;#8221; This was helpful to be able to scan the room and get a sense of the progress. We used this at software carpentry as well, but it was definitely more helpful as an instructor than as a student, because you got an implicit sense of progress, without having to check in personally with&amp;nbsp;everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what the students said they&amp;nbsp;liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In-class verbal feedback (everyone has to give one feedback, alternate good and bad, no repeats)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working in&amp;nbsp;pairs &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hands-on&amp;nbsp;activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleanly&amp;nbsp;organized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could go at your own&amp;nbsp;pace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My partner was very&amp;nbsp;helpful!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learned&amp;nbsp;IPython&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anonymous written feedback. All of these are direct quotes.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thorough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progressive - ideas built upon each other&amp;nbsp;well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paired&amp;nbsp;activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was a great session - should have done this in the first week. Your tutorial was &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EXCELLENT&lt;/span&gt;. It would be nice to have this introduced earlier, in this manner. You&amp;#8217;re a great instructor. Great job and thank&amp;nbsp;you!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very nice. Work on IPython&amp;nbsp;exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very well put together exercise, referenceable for the&amp;nbsp;future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very practical&amp;nbsp;skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Step by step instructions with logic very&amp;nbsp;helpful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Awesome worksheet, really well made. My favorite parts were the ones that made me think harder, so the worksheet could be even&amp;nbsp;harder.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good instructions on&amp;nbsp;platform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to&amp;nbsp;follow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IPython&amp;nbsp;format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thanks for your patience! I liked the tutorial a lot! Using IPython is fun&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The steps and instructions were clear and built on each other. I would be happy if all homework was set up in this&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions for getting set up with downloading an IPython notebook, and having to &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; and navigate to that directory, and start up an IPython notebook were confusing and need to be rewritten or completely reworked. Maybe give them a &lt;code&gt;wget&lt;/code&gt; or similar command? Then they&amp;#8217;ll be directly in that folder where the &lt;code&gt;.ipynb&lt;/code&gt; was downloaded to, and don&amp;#8217;t have to do any navigation. This took up a good 15 minutes at the beginning, that could have been used on programming&amp;nbsp;instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows was a much larger impediment than I thought. The first part of the lesson was performing Unix commands such as &lt;code&gt;head&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tail&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;wc&lt;/code&gt;, and searching for a command to count the number of columns in a file (ends up being either &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; or a combo of &lt;code&gt;head&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;wc&lt;/code&gt;). I didn&amp;#8217;t plan for this, or test the lesson on a Windows machine, but half the class was using Windows. So that&amp;#8217;s definitely something I will plan for in the future. I felt really&amp;nbsp;bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what the students said could be&amp;nbsp;improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In-class verbal feedback&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Felt rushed for&amp;nbsp;me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show the results on my computer, as well as hands&amp;nbsp;on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard to get started without the right&amp;nbsp;programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;too much help&lt;/strong&gt; in the instructions [This one took me off&amp;nbsp;guard!]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windows&amp;nbsp;:(&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Memes&amp;nbsp;:(&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anonymous written feedback&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad. Windows machines.&amp;nbsp;Bad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would be nice to work with genomics&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s hard for me not to be the&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;driver&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Umm, too much&amp;nbsp;feedback?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard to find equivalent commands for Windows on my own because I don&amp;#8217;t know how to parse through other people&amp;#8217;s tips and know which one will work or not. Not your fault&amp;nbsp;though!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There should be resources and instructions on how to make this applicable to our own&amp;nbsp;work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Ugly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows&amp;nbsp;:(&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="teaching"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="programming"></category></entry><entry><title>Re: “Shirtgate”</title><link href="/re-shirtgate-.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-16T11:28:00-08:00</published><updated>2014-11-16T11:28:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-11-16:/re-shirtgate-.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Re &lt;a href="http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2014/11/a-pornographer-and-atheist-explains-why-the-science-guys-shirt-crash-landed/"&gt;&amp;#8220;shirtgate&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; (link is to a reasonable summary and rebuttal that I don&amp;#8217;t completely agree&amp;nbsp;with.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like it&amp;#8217;s overly simplistic to let one woman&amp;#8217;s voice stand for all women, I also think it&amp;#8217;s a jump to say that the women on this shirt represent every woman ever. I&amp;#8217;m me, and there&amp;#8217;s no other me, right? I&amp;#8217;m not on this shirt, and I don&amp;#8217;t see my career in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; melting in front of me because of this&amp;nbsp;shirt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree that this shirt says, as the linked article&amp;nbsp;claims, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every woman working on this project, every woman working on a similar project, every woman working in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt;, every woman aspiring to work in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; — this is what I think of you. Every girl dreaming of working in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEM&lt;/span&gt; someday — this is what I’ll think of you when you’re grown up. Tits and ass. That’s what you are to&amp;nbsp;me.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shirt says, these specific women, on this shirt, are hot and surrounded by awesome sci-fi imagery. These women could be excellent scientists! Their sexiness has nothing to do with how scientifically capable they are. Maybe the models are brilliant engineers, who knows. To me, this is a very limited interpretation of the shirt, &amp;#8220;they are hot therefore they are dumb and incapable of other things,&amp;#8221; which is exactly the kind of interpretation I would like to be&amp;nbsp;combating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel offended by this shirt, that&amp;#8217;s your right and I&amp;#8217;ll fight for your right to say that. If he outright said &amp;#8220;No way women could have made this comet landing happen, they&amp;#8217;re too stupid,&amp;#8221; I would completely agree that this person is sexist. However, I personally don&amp;#8217;t feel that this choice of attire represents me at all. I&amp;#8217;m a lot more complex of a ladybeing than what&amp;#8217;s being represented on that garment, and I&amp;#8217;m not going to pretend that what someone else wore is an indication of my own&amp;nbsp;abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; agree it&amp;#8217;s an incredibly distracting shirt, a terrible fashion choice, and he needs a wardrobe upgrade. That&amp;#8217;s the kind of controversy I&amp;#8217;d stand&amp;nbsp;behind.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="social media"></category><category term="feminism"></category></entry><entry><title>No longer actively developing prettyplotlib</title><link href="/blog/2014/10/06/no-longer-actively-developing-prettyplotlib/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-10-06T10:10:39-07:00</published><updated>2014-10-06T10:10:39-07:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-10-06:/blog/2014/10/06/no-longer-actively-developing-prettyplotlib/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is with heavy heart that I announce that I am no longer actively developing &lt;a href="https://github.com/olgabot/prettyplotlib"&gt;&lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I just don&amp;#8217;t have the bandwidth available to do the project justice. It was a fantastic experience to&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is with heavy heart that I announce that I am no longer actively developing &lt;a href="https://github.com/olgabot/prettyplotlib"&gt;&lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was a fantastic experience to bundle up that piece of code and share it with the world, and discover that there are many other people who want pretty plots. Over the last year, I discovered a much better visualization library in Python called &lt;a href="https://github.com/mwaskom/seaborn"&gt;&lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is much more mature and covers more ground than &lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt; ever could. From working on &lt;a href="https://github.com/mwaskom/seaborn/pull/230"&gt;clustered heatmaps&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve become a much better Python programmer, and am forever grateful to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/michaelwaskom"&gt;Michael Waskom&lt;/a&gt; for creating&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;, to get the &lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt; style,&amp;nbsp;do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;seaborn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;ticks&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;palette&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Set2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And to remove &amp;#8220;chartjunk&amp;#8221;,&amp;nbsp;do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sns.despine()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have discrete pull requests, I will accept them, but I personally will no longer fix&amp;nbsp;bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to all the &lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt; users, especially &lt;a href="http://www.pgbovine.net/"&gt;Phillip Guo&lt;/a&gt; for tweeting about it and setting off the publicity storm, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/olgabot/prettyplotlib/graphs/contributors"&gt;all the contributors&lt;/a&gt; who took my measly code and made it great. I&amp;#8217;ve learned so much from the Python open source community and am so thankful that it is so easy to learn from others in this wonderful&amp;nbsp;environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to check out what I&amp;#8217;ve been working on instead, take a look at &lt;a href="https://github.com/YeoLab/flotilla"&gt;&lt;code&gt;flotilla&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the package I&amp;#8217;ve been working on with &lt;a href="https://github.com/mlovci"&gt;Michael Lovci&lt;/a&gt; for reproducible single-cell analysis. The package is still in its infancy (read: be prepared for bugs), and we are actively developing&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="visualization"></category><category term="prettyplotlib"></category><category term="seaborn"></category><category term="flotilla"></category></entry><entry><title>Migration to Github.io!</title><link href="/migration-to-github-io-English.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-25T08:58:51-07:00</published><updated>2014-09-25T08:58:51-07:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-09-25:/migration-to-github-io-English.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Migrated my blog from Tumblr to&amp;nbsp;Github.io&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I moved my blog from &lt;a href="http://www.tumblr.com/"&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt; for several&amp;nbsp;reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write posts in Markdown and IPython notebooks so figures, code, and LaTeX markup would show up&amp;nbsp;fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easily back up my posts. Before, I wrote my posts in &lt;a href="http://simplenote.com/"&gt;Simplenote&lt;/a&gt; and then copy-pasted to Tumblr, but I didn&amp;#8217;t like&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t use the re-blogging or following aspects of Tumblr much so I didn&amp;#8217;t see the advantages of that&amp;nbsp;network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awesome &lt;a href="http://www.pelicanthemes.com/"&gt;customizable themes&lt;/a&gt; using&amp;nbsp;Pelican.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few drawbacks, most notably, the comments from previous posts are still tied to the Tumblr website, because Tumblr doesn&amp;#8217;t use slugs (e.g. &amp;#8220;&lt;code&gt;migration-to-github-io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;) for its webpage names, instead it uses some random number generator for keeping track of posts, e.g &amp;#8220;post/72680703972&amp;#8221;. And because &lt;a href="https://disqus.com/"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; uses the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; from the post to map it back to its database, and I couldn&amp;#8217;t get the original mapping :( So comments for old posts will be back on&amp;nbsp;Tumblr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m excited for a new start with&amp;nbsp;blogging!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="github"></category><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>The second article</title><link href="/blog/2012/12/01/the-second-article/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-01T10:02:00-08:00</published><updated>2012-12-01T10:02:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-12-01:/blog/2012/12/01/the-second-article/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;See below intra-site link examples in Markdown&amp;nbsp;format.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;See below intra-site link examples in Markdown&amp;nbsp;format.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>