<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Science, meet productivity</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/olga-botvinnik.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2015-02-22T13:29:35-08:00</updated><entry><title>2014 Annual Review</title><link href="/blog/2015/02/22/2014-annual-review/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-02-22T13:29:35-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2015-02-22:blog/2015/02/22/2014-annual-review/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I subscribed to &lt;a href="http://jamesclear.com/"&gt;James Clear&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s blog and his writing and advice has resonated with me. The last time I felt like someone was speaking directly through me was Cal Newport&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/"&gt;Study Hacks&lt;/a&gt; blog, which I discovered during undergrad, and I felt it directly addressed the issues I was having with keeping up with my intense&amp;nbsp;courseload. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Clear posted his &lt;a href="http://jamesclear.com/2014-annual-review"&gt;2014 Annual Review&lt;/a&gt; in December, and it reminded me of how we do annual self-evaluations for work. I read through my evaluation for 2013 and enjoyed reflecting back on that time, how much I did then, what didn&amp;#8217;t go well, and what I&amp;#8217;ve learned since. So I&amp;#8217;m going to follow his template with the following three&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What went well this&amp;nbsp;year?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What didn’t go so well this&amp;nbsp;year?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What am I working&amp;nbsp;toward?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. What went well this&amp;nbsp;year?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellowships.&lt;/strong&gt; This year, I was the first and sole recipient of the &lt;a href="http://numfocus.org/news/2014/07/01/john-hunter-technology-fellowship-awarded/"&gt;NumFOCUS John Hunter Technology Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;. I was thrilled to receive it, especially because I thought I had no chance of getting it. From the wording of the announcement, which said &amp;#8220;postdoctoral scientists or senior graduate students,&amp;#8221; I thought I wasn&amp;#8217;t seasoned enough, and I figured people who work on &lt;a href="http://scikit-learn.org/stable/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;IPython&lt;/a&gt; would apply and definitely get it over me. Plus I couldn&amp;#8217;t think of anyone who would be willing to be my Software Mentor, as required for the application. Thankfully, at &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2014/"&gt;PyCon&lt;/a&gt;, I was talking to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ctitusbrown"&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt; and mentioned that I wanted to apply to this fellowship but thought I wouldn&amp;#8217;t get it, and that didn&amp;#8217;t have a Software Mentor. Immediately, he dismissed my doubts and offered be my Software Mentor, on the spot! I almost cried because I was so happy and surprised to hear someone believe in me so strongly, especially because for the previous year I had been getting major shade and negativity from certain peers back home, which majorly impacted my mental state and made me feel constantly&amp;nbsp;inadequate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python involvement.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#8217;m very proud to have contributed to the &lt;a href="http://web.stanford.edu/~mwaskom/software/seaborn/index.html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; statistical data visualization Python package, specifically creating the first-ever (that I know of) single-line clustered heatmap function in Python! It was months of work, and couldn&amp;#8217;t have been done without the input from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mike_t_lovci"&gt;Mike Lovci&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cdeboever3"&gt;Christopher DeBoever&lt;/a&gt;. Plus now I have more clout to evangelize Python for bioinformatics research&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passed Qualifying Exam!&lt;/strong&gt; On May 15th, 2014, I proved my competency to a group of three professors, who all agreed that I can move on to the next stage of graduate school! I spent a solid month writing and working on my presentation and was &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; nervous and stressed about it, so it was very satisfying to be&amp;nbsp;over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Travel and conferences&lt;/strong&gt; Last year I traveled&amp;nbsp;to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strata 2014 in Santa Clara,&amp;nbsp;California&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyCon 2014 in Montreal,&amp;nbsp;Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-quals vacation in Cabo San Lucas,&amp;nbsp;Mexico&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single-cell genomics conference in Stockholm, Sweden. Plus Italy (Rome and Venice)&amp;nbsp;afterwards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PyData 2014 (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IQksDvFl2_8"&gt;gave a talk!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been a great experience to visit these places and make new friends in the Python, data science, and single-cell communities. Looking forward to more this&amp;nbsp;year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photography&lt;/strong&gt; While I haven&amp;#8217;t publicly shared much photography, I&amp;#8217;ve taken lots of photos on these different trips. The Europe trip was especially good, because I purposely tested out different settings in low light and other tough situations, and I spent a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOT&lt;/span&gt; of time watching LightRoom tutorials on editing, and learned a lot of new techniques that I&amp;#8217;ve been practicing with new&amp;nbsp;photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal relationships.&lt;/strong&gt; I had some tough interpersonal issues this year and in talking through it with a friend, they recommended the book &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Difficult-Conversations-Discuss-What-Matters/dp/0143118447"&gt;Difficult Conversations&lt;/a&gt;. I highly recommend this book to everyone, because difficult conversations happen every day, and this will provide you the tools and perspectives you need to understand them. I can honestly say that the book has changed my life and helped me critically evaluate everyone&amp;#8217;s role in a tricky spot, and come up with strategies in how to approach these situations tactfully. Tact has never been my strong suit, so these lessons were&amp;nbsp;eye-opening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. What didn&amp;#8217;t go so well this&amp;nbsp;year?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not being afraid of the unknown or difficult.&lt;/strong&gt; These first few years of graduate school, if some task took steps that I couldn&amp;#8217;t clearly visualize, or I could see them but I thought they were too hard, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t do it, and my research would suffer as a result. For example, I&amp;#8217;ve been putting off doing a complicated operation on a bunch of sequences that would help my research in ways I can&amp;#8217;t comprehend now, but it was so nebulous to me that I didn&amp;#8217;t even want to attempt it. Or I&amp;#8217;d get some result and not know how to interpret it, and the solution was to go to the literature and read a bunch of papers about those genes, but that&amp;#8217;s too hard so I didn&amp;#8217;t want to do&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blogging.&lt;/strong&gt; I published 10 total blog posts in 2014. I switched to hosting my blog using github.io rather than Tumblr in 2014. I thought my lack of blogging was a result of my blog being on Tumblr and being ugly and annoying to write IPython notebook style blog posts for it, rather than using markdown/IPython entries. I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; have 6 blog posts after September, compared to 4 pre-September, so the change helped. But I still feel I could have blogged more, even small random things I found helpful like that bit about using &lt;a href="http://blog.olgabotvinnik.com/different-branches-different-ipython-notebooks-.html"&gt;different git branches in different IPython notebooks&lt;/a&gt;, which was a great discovery for me in my development workflow. I think part of my lack of posts was also the misguided belief that every post has to be a gigantic, perfectly crafted tome, when it&amp;#8217;s fine to have a concise 100-word&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publishing.&lt;/strong&gt; I didn&amp;#8217;t complete any scientific publications this year. While it&amp;#8217;s not common for a 2nd-year graduate student to publish a paper, I thought I was working hard towards that goal, but in reality, I didn&amp;#8217;t understand the magnitude of work that goes into a publication. I also think my &lt;em&gt;being afraid of the unknown&lt;/em&gt;, not knowing how to do something and being afraid of being wrong, also played into&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular progress reviews.&lt;/strong&gt; Every once in a while I put together weekly progress reviews of what I did that week and what&amp;#8217;s the plan for the next week. It makes me feel good, and it works for a bit, but then I give it up because I think &amp;#8220;ehh, I&amp;#8217;ll just remember what I need to do.&amp;#8221; I feel I spend too much time on trivial things like reformatting code or making some plot look just slightly better (but not necessarily more readable), rather than moving on to the next&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python involvement.&lt;/strong&gt; You may wonder why this topic is in both the &amp;#8220;went well&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;didn&amp;#8217;t go so well&amp;#8221; categories. While I&amp;#8217;m happy with my &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt; contributions, I haven&amp;#8217;t been as happy with other things. There&amp;#8217;s been features I&amp;#8217;ve wanted to add to &lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (read gzipped files over the internet) and other visualization features to &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;, I haven&amp;#8217;t gotten around to doing them. I did start subscribing to &lt;code&gt;matplotlib-devel&lt;/code&gt; and watching the &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt; repo for all issues, and replied to a few, but I&amp;#8217;m still afraid that I don&amp;#8217;t have anything to add to the&amp;nbsp;conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sustaining interest.&lt;/strong&gt; As both &lt;a href="http://jamesclear.com/stay-focused"&gt;James Clear&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2009/06/22/on-the-value-of-hard-focus/"&gt;Cal Newport&lt;/a&gt; have discussed, it&amp;#8217;s consistent, sustained effort and focus over a long period of time which generates results. I find it really easy to start something fresh and new, and I struggle with maintaining interest in something long enough to reap the rewards at the&amp;nbsp;end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cello&lt;/strong&gt; Last January I performed a small cello concert for my friends, and worked really hard practicing a lot for it. But this last six months I haven&amp;#8217;t practiced much. Part of it is my teacher had personal commitments that prevented him from teaching for some time, but I think the more major part is that I didn&amp;#8217;t pay for my lessons. I was supposed to help him with his &lt;a href="http://www.celloloftmusic.com/cellosophy/"&gt;Cellosophy&lt;/a&gt; cello app, but honestly I just bit off more than I could chew. The coding was going to be for the instructor website in &lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3.js&lt;/a&gt; and that&amp;#8217;s not part of my core competency, so it was a lot of work for me to just make a bar chart. And so I didn&amp;#8217;t do a good job of collaborating&amp;#8230; and as a result I didn&amp;#8217;t ascribe as much value as I should have to my lessons, and didn&amp;#8217;t invest as much time in them. Once I get back into cello, I&amp;#8217;m going to pay for them. As expensive as they are, they are worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fitness&lt;/strong&gt; I was very good about going to yoga and exercising 4+ times a week, but something happened around August and I stopped working out as much. I gained some weight and lost fitness, and I&amp;#8217;m now trying to change that (see next&amp;nbsp;section).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. What am I working&amp;nbsp;toward?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular progress reviews + Time-boxing.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve started &lt;a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2013/12/21/deep-habits-the-importance-of-planning-every-minute-of-your-work-day/"&gt;planning my workday&lt;/a&gt; carefully in a &lt;a href="http://amzn.com/8867322729?tag=sciencmeetpro-20"&gt;Moleskine daily planner&lt;/a&gt; (in green, my favorite color). This is part of what my colleague &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/leenyann"&gt;Colleen Stoyas&lt;/a&gt; likes to call &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/LeenyAnn/status/563335731070771200"&gt;#projectGETONYOGAME&lt;/a&gt;. Writing down how I spend my hours has been a very effective way for me to keep track of where the time goes, especially when it turns out that what I thought was a 30 minute break turned into an hour and a half of eating and chatting&amp;#8230; yikes. I&amp;#8217;m taking the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1585425524/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1585425524&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=sciencmeetpro-20&amp;amp;linkId=PJBK7XP4R2HJIX6N"&gt;Now Habit&lt;/a&gt; approach of not trying to change my habits dramatically, but writing everything down and paying attention to what I&amp;#8217;m doing. Below are some example schedules I&amp;#8217;ve created, for days that went as planned, and others that did not. The images have been blurred for&amp;nbsp;privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a sample day that went quite well, and I mostly stuck to my schedule. You&amp;#8217;ll notice I have some random notes on the side of reminders of people to meet with, and I even drew out a network. However, I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; end up taking a 1.5 hour break from lingering around and chatting, which I probably could have shortened and ended my day&amp;nbsp;earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/qZ-uwUliG-UVLt8fAerezK-guKImO5oWBv3wjSuSGesKUKYJ75xSBtD07FV8pWaQJe0ZRw=w2560-h1318"&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/qZ-uwUliG-UVLt8fAerezK-guKImO5oWBv3wjSuSGesKUKYJ75xSBtD07FV8pWaQJe0ZRw=w2560-h1318" alt="Example hour plan for a day that went mostly as planned" style="width: 200px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is an example day that didn&amp;#8217;t go as planned, where I started late and thus deviated from the schedule quite a bit. I also got the time wrong for when I was supposed to be teaching data cleaning (2pm not 12pm), so that changed things up too. While this didn&amp;#8217;t go completely as planned, I was able to squeeze a lot of work&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/COL5YRxiP__y0uuyiz_MsmWovJIYVvoBpHDlim8Iv8i2bEWMnSyuduE3cP543HyrvtH5VA=w2560-h1318"&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/COL5YRxiP__y0uuyiz_MsmWovJIYVvoBpHDlim8Iv8i2bEWMnSyuduE3cP543HyrvtH5VA=w2560-h1318" alt="Example hour plan for a day that didn't go as planned" style="width: 200px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publishing.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;#8217;s hard for me to call a project &amp;#8220;done enough,&amp;#8221; and yet this is exactly what I need to do to be able to publish. I have a couple conference abstract and presentation deadlines coming up in the next few months which will help me to focus on creating &amp;#8220;publishable units.&amp;#8221; Plus I have my advancement in a month, so that will be a big push to get manuscripts ready so I can say that certain projects are at least &amp;#8220;submitted&amp;#8221; to my&amp;nbsp;committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://grad.ucsd.edu/progress/candidacy.html"&gt;Advancing to candidacy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; In our program, the &amp;#8220;Advancement Exam&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Senate Exam&amp;#8221; is when you show your committee what research you&amp;#8217;ve accomplished so far, and your plan for your PhD. I&amp;#8217;m very nervous for it, and have been doing a lot of background reading to be able to motivate why my projects are important, and why they make sense to be done together. I&amp;#8217;m planning to do this in March, so wish me&amp;nbsp;luck!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fitness.&lt;/strong&gt; I signed up for my first half-marathon, the &lt;a href="http://www.lajollahalfmarathon.com/"&gt;La Jolla Half Marathon&lt;/a&gt;! I&amp;#8217;ve been training hard for it, maybe a little too hard because I hurt my knee and am resting it now (no running for 1&amp;nbsp;week!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photography.&lt;/strong&gt; I have a bunch of photos I&amp;#8217;ve taken of nature, flowers, architecture, scenery, and LegoLand that I use as backgrounds, and I&amp;#8217;m planning on sharing them as an album. As motivation, I&amp;#8217;m also planning to apply to this year&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2014/09/ubuntu-14-10-wallpaper-contest-winners"&gt;Ubuntu Wallpaper Contest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cello.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#8217;m going to start scheduling time to play cello, even if its only fifteen minutes, it&amp;#8217;s still an important&amp;nbsp;investment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="review"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="professional"></category><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>Bio-what?</title><link href="/blog/2015/02/22/bio-what/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-02-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2015-02-22:blog/2015/02/22/bio-what/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I tell people I do &amp;#8220;bioinformatics,&amp;#8221; the response is usually &amp;#8220;bio-&lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;?&amp;#8221; And honestly, bioinformatics is hard to define even for people &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WITHIN&lt;/span&gt; the field. In this post I will describe what I see as the two main threads of&amp;nbsp;bioinformatics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, there&amp;#8217;s the issue of naming. To some people, &amp;#8220;Computational Biology&amp;#8221; is separate from &amp;#8220;Bioinformatics,&amp;#8221; but two people rarely agree on exactly what constitutes one or the other. Secondly, our PhD program is named &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Bioinformatics and Systems Biology&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;, and according to my friend on the systems biology side who worked in a Harvard lab during undergrad before coming to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UC&lt;/span&gt;-San Diego, there&amp;#8217;s a huge difference between &amp;#8220;East Coast Systems Biology&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;West Coast Systems Biology,&amp;#8221; even though I can&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, there&amp;#8217;s a huge range of topics that consist of bioinformatics in one way or another. The way I see it, there&amp;#8217;s two main divisions: &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Classic Bioinformatics&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Applied Bioinformatics.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; These should be taken with a heavy grain of salt, as I am a newcomer to the Bioinformatics field. These are my opinions on the current state, not absolute truth. Additionally, these two &amp;#8220;halves&amp;#8221; are symbiotic, and need each other to sustain&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Classic&amp;nbsp;Bioinformatics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where it all started. It used to be that when people thought of bioinformatics, they thought of comparing sequences. A few years ago I read a blog post that stated &amp;#8220;All of bioinformatics is essentially &lt;code&gt;strcmp&lt;/code&gt; [string compare],&amp;#8221; which made my blood boil because the subtleties of comparing these strings requires sophisticated algorithms to account for gaps, substitutions, and repetitive regions. Most of the tools below are analyzing strings&amp;nbsp;or &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus here is to make sense and organize what we have of biological data into organized data&amp;nbsp;structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the algorithms and tools that we learn in our first-year graduate school classes,&amp;nbsp;like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/98/17/9748.full"&gt;De Bruijn graphs for genome&amp;nbsp;assembly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=586673"&gt;Genome rearrangements and sorting by&amp;nbsp;reversals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smith%E2%80%93Waterman_algorithm"&gt;Smith-Waterman local alignment of&amp;nbsp;sequences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Needleman%E2%80%93Wunsch_algorithm"&gt;Needleman-Wunsch global alignment of&amp;nbsp;sequences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://genomebiology.com/2009/10/3/R25"&gt;Burrows-Wheeler transform for aligning reads to the&amp;nbsp;genome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://genes.mit.edu/burgelab/maxent/Xmaxentscan_scoreseq.html"&gt;Maximum Entropy determination of splice site&amp;nbsp;strengths&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/ged-lab/khmer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;-mer counting and&amp;nbsp;filtering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nbt/journal/v22/n10/pdf/nbt1004-1315.pdf"&gt;Hidden Markov Models for genome and protein structure and domain&amp;nbsp;prediction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.psrg.csail.mit.edu/pubs/BarGifJaa-ismb01.pdf"&gt;Optimal leaf ordering for hierarchical&amp;nbsp;clustering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v415/n6868/full/415180a.html"&gt;Mass spectrometry for&amp;nbsp;proteomics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3398611/"&gt;Cyclic peptide sequencing by mass&amp;nbsp;spectrometry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see this as &lt;em&gt;Computer science applied to&amp;nbsp;biology.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Applied&amp;nbsp;Bioinformatics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where we are now. This is closer to what I do on a daily basis. Honestly, I don&amp;#8217;t build any of the algorithms above, but I do need to understand them to know where my data is coming&amp;nbsp;from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, the skills I learned in my classes was a good basis for the broad field of biology, but I barely use them on a day-to-day basis. Mostly&amp;nbsp;I &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus here is to attribute &lt;em&gt;biological function&lt;/em&gt; to&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030129"&gt;Bayesian network&amp;nbsp;inference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;Network&amp;nbsp;flow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see this as &lt;em&gt;Data science applied to biology.&lt;/em&gt; These require the output of the &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Classic Bioinformatics&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; tools, and use statistics, machine learning, and other applied tools to extract&amp;nbsp;information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Classic vs Applied and Awards by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISCB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#8217;s interesting is that this division is especially evident in the awardees of the &lt;a href="http://www.iscb.org/"&gt;International Society of Computational Biology&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISCB&lt;/span&gt;), where the Overton awards to early-career scientists tend to be more &amp;#8220;Applied,&amp;#8221; and the Senior Scientist tend to be more&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;Classic.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I am human, I certainly may have missed a paper or two that pushed one person into one of the other categories, and I am happy to correct any&amp;nbsp;errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overton Award&amp;nbsp;(Early-career)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2015: Applied] &lt;a href="http://www.iscb.org/iscb-awards/2383"&gt;Curtis Huttenhower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Applied] Justification: &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19246570?dopt=Abstract"&gt;Functional maps of the human genome&lt;/a&gt; Analysis of large-scale microbiome&amp;nbsp;datasets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2014] &lt;a href="http://www.iscb.org/iscb-awards/2225"&gt;Dana Pe&amp;#8217;er&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Applied] Justification: &lt;a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/17/suppl_1/S215.full.pdf"&gt;Inferring subnetworks from perturbed expression profiles using Bayesian&amp;nbsp;Networks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2013] &lt;a href="http://www.iscb.org/iscb-awards/1837"&gt;Goncalo Abecasis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Classic] Justification: &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0002929707622538"&gt;Quantitative Test Loci in nuclear families&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v30/n1/full/ng786.html"&gt;Gene flow trees&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/25/16/2078.short"&gt;Sequence Alignment Map (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SAM&lt;/span&gt;)&amp;nbsp;format&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2012] &lt;a href="http://www.iscb.org/iscb-awards/1224"&gt;Ziv Bar-Joseph&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Classic] Justification: &lt;a href="http://www.psrg.csail.mit.edu/pubs/BarGifJaa-ismb01.pdf"&gt;Optimal Leaf Ordering&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/331/6014/183"&gt;Maximal Independent Sets in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2011] &lt;a href="http://www.iscb.org/iscb-awards/1117"&gt;Olga Troyanskaya&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Applied] Justification: &lt;a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/17/6/520.full.pdf"&gt;Missing value imputation for microarrays&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/100/14/8348.long"&gt;A Bayesian framework for combining heterogeneous data sources for gene function prediction (in Saccharomyces&amp;nbsp;cerevisiae)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2010] &lt;a href=""&gt;Steven E.&amp;nbsp;Brenner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2009] &lt;a href=""&gt;Trey&amp;nbsp;Ideker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2008] &lt;a href=""&gt;Aviv&amp;nbsp;Regev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2007] &lt;a href=""&gt;Eran&amp;nbsp;Segal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2006] &lt;a href=""&gt;Mathieu&amp;nbsp;Blanchette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2005] &lt;a href=""&gt;Ewan&amp;nbsp;Birney&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2004] &lt;a href=""&gt;Uri&amp;nbsp;Alon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2003] &lt;a href=""&gt;Jim&amp;nbsp;Kent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2002] &lt;a href=""&gt;David&amp;nbsp;Baker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2001] &lt;a href=""&gt;Christopher B.&amp;nbsp;Burge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Senior Scientist Accomplishment&amp;nbsp;Prize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2015] &lt;a href=""&gt;Cyrus&amp;nbsp;Chothia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2014] &lt;a href="http://www.iscb.org/iscb-awards/2224"&gt;Gene Myers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Classic] Justification: &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2231712?dopt=Citation"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BLAST&lt;/span&gt; aka Basic Local Alignment Search&amp;nbsp;Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2013] &lt;a href=""&gt;David&amp;nbsp;Eisenberg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2012] &lt;a href=""&gt;Gunnar von&amp;nbsp;Heijne&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2011] &lt;a href=""&gt;Michael&amp;nbsp;Ashburner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2010] &lt;a href=""&gt;Chris&amp;nbsp;Sander&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2009] &lt;a href=""&gt;Webb&amp;nbsp;Miller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2008] &lt;a href=""&gt;David&amp;nbsp;Haussler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2007] &lt;a href=""&gt;Temple&amp;nbsp;Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2006] &lt;a href=""&gt;Michael&amp;nbsp;Waterman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2005] &lt;a href=""&gt;Janet&amp;nbsp;Thornton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2004] &lt;a href=""&gt;David&amp;nbsp;Lipman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2003] &lt;a href=""&gt;David&amp;nbsp;Sankoff &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="science"></category><category term="bioinformatics"></category></entry><entry><title>Teaching “Data cleaning”</title><link href="/blog/2015/01/29/teaching-data-cleaning/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-29T13:51:43-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2015-01-29:blog/2015/01/29/teaching-data-cleaning/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our compute cluster is down for maintenance, so obviously instead of working on my advancement exam presentation, I&amp;#8217;m gonna write a blog&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I taught a 1-hour lesson on &amp;#8220;Cleaning data&amp;#8221; for graduate students in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UCSD&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BIOM262&lt;/span&gt;: Quantitative Methods in Genetics class. Here is the &lt;a href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/gist/olgabot/edebccd736d051d8a1c7"&gt;IPython notebook&lt;/a&gt; that I used. While designing the lesson, I used concepts I learned from &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s &lt;a href="http://teaching.software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Training for instructors&lt;/a&gt;, such&amp;nbsp;as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing the lesson incrementally, so every step builds upon&amp;nbsp;itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When designing a lesson, have the final task in mind and teach to&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being as clear as possible for each&amp;nbsp;step&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the workshop, I again implemented things we learned in software carpentry, such as working in pairs and using stickie notes to indicate progress. Overall, I thought it went quite well, with students being engaged for most of the time. Here&amp;#8217;s the results of what went well and what could be&amp;nbsp;improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the things I thought went&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everyone worked in pairs&lt;/strong&gt;. Before we split into pairs, I surveyed the class to check for previous experience with &lt;a href="http://www.python.org/"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;IPython Notebook&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/"&gt;pandas&lt;/a&gt;. Then, the person who has &lt;strong&gt;less&lt;/strong&gt; experience was the one who did all the typing (aka &amp;#8220;driving&amp;#8221; in pair-programming parlance), and the more experienced person wasn&amp;#8217;t allowed to type. We did this at the software carpentry training while doing a &lt;a href="https://github.com/"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; exercise. I paired with someone who was less experienced with Github, and it was a good experience for me to have to sit on my hands and talk through every step. This was very useful because the more experienced person had to be explicit and describe every step, and the less experienced person automatically had a mentor to ask &amp;#8220;dumb&amp;#8221; questions to, without having to grab an instructor. An additional benefit is that when working in pairs, you&amp;#8217;re held more accountable, so you can&amp;#8217;t just do some exercises and then switch to your email or facebook, because your partner is right&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Used pink and blue stickies to show progress.&lt;/strong&gt; Pink was &amp;#8220;still working&amp;#8221; and blue was &amp;#8220;done.&amp;#8221; This was helpful to be able to scan the room and get a sense of the progress. We used this at software carpentry as well, but it was definitely more helpful as an instructor than as a student, because you got an implicit sense of progress, without having to check in personally with&amp;nbsp;everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what the students said they&amp;nbsp;liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In-class verbal feedback (everyone has to give one feedback, alternate good and bad, no repeats)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working in&amp;nbsp;pairs &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hands-on&amp;nbsp;activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleanly&amp;nbsp;organized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could go at your own&amp;nbsp;pace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My partner was very&amp;nbsp;helpful!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learned&amp;nbsp;IPython&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anonymous written feedback. All of these are direct quotes.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thorough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progressive - ideas built upon each other&amp;nbsp;well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paired&amp;nbsp;activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was a great session - should have done this in the first week. Your tutorial was &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EXCELLENT&lt;/span&gt;. It would be nice to have this introduced earlier, in this manner. You&amp;#8217;re a great instructor. Great job and thank&amp;nbsp;you!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very nice. Work on IPython&amp;nbsp;exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very well put together exercise, referenceable for the&amp;nbsp;future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very practical&amp;nbsp;skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Step by step instructions with logic very&amp;nbsp;helpful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Awesome worksheet, really well made. My favorite parts were the ones that made me think harder, so the worksheet could be even&amp;nbsp;harder.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good instructions on&amp;nbsp;platform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to&amp;nbsp;follow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IPython&amp;nbsp;format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thanks for your patience! I liked the tutorial a lot! Using IPython is fun&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The steps and instructions were clear and built on each other. I would be happy if all homework was set up in this&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions for getting set up with downloading an IPython notebook, and having to &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; and navigate to that directory, and start up an IPython notebook were confusing and need to be rewritten or completely reworked. Maybe give them a &lt;code&gt;wget&lt;/code&gt; or similar command? Then they&amp;#8217;ll be directly in that folder where the &lt;code&gt;.ipynb&lt;/code&gt; was downloaded to, and don&amp;#8217;t have to do any navigation. This took up a good 15 minutes at the beginning, that could have been used on programming&amp;nbsp;instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows was a much larger impediment than I thought. The first part of the lesson was performing Unix commands such as &lt;code&gt;head&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tail&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;wc&lt;/code&gt;, and searching for a command to count the number of columns in a file (ends up being either &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; or a combo of &lt;code&gt;head&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;wc&lt;/code&gt;). I didn&amp;#8217;t plan for this, or test the lesson on a Windows machine, but half the class was using Windows. So that&amp;#8217;s definitely something I will plan for in the future. I felt really&amp;nbsp;bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what the students said could be&amp;nbsp;improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In-class verbal feedback&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Felt rushed for&amp;nbsp;me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show the results on my computer, as well as hands&amp;nbsp;on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard to get started without the right&amp;nbsp;programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;too much help&lt;/strong&gt; in the instructions [This one took me off&amp;nbsp;guard!]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windows&amp;nbsp;:(&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Memes&amp;nbsp;:(&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anonymous written feedback&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad. Windows machines.&amp;nbsp;Bad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would be nice to work with genomics&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s hard for me not to be the&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;driver&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Umm, too much&amp;nbsp;feedback?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard to find equivalent commands for Windows on my own because I don&amp;#8217;t know how to parse through other people&amp;#8217;s tips and know which one will work or not. Not your fault&amp;nbsp;though!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There should be resources and instructions on how to make this applicable to our own&amp;nbsp;work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Ugly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows&amp;nbsp;:(&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="teaching"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="programming"></category></entry><entry><title>No longer actively developing prettyplotlib</title><link href="/blog/2014/10/06/no-longer-actively-developing-prettyplotlib/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-06T10:10:39-07:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2014-10-06:blog/2014/10/06/no-longer-actively-developing-prettyplotlib/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is with heavy heart that I announce that I am no longer actively developing &lt;a href="https://github.com/olgabot/prettyplotlib"&gt;&lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was a fantastic experience to bundle up that piece of code and share it with the world, and discover that there are many other people who want pretty plots. Over the last year, I discovered a much better visualization library in Python called &lt;a href="https://github.com/mwaskom/seaborn"&gt;&lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is much more mature and covers more ground than &lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt; ever could. From working on &lt;a href="https://github.com/mwaskom/seaborn/pull/230"&gt;clustered heatmaps&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve become a much better Python programmer, and am forever grateful to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/michaelwaskom"&gt;Michael Waskom&lt;/a&gt; for creating&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;seaborn&lt;/code&gt;, to get the &lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt; style,&amp;nbsp;do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;seaborn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;ticks&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;palette&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;Set2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And to remove &amp;#8220;chartjunk&amp;#8221;,&amp;nbsp;do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sns.despine()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have discrete pull requests, I will accept them, but I personally will no longer fix&amp;nbsp;bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you to all the &lt;code&gt;prettyplotlib&lt;/code&gt; users, especially &lt;a href="http://www.pgbovine.net/"&gt;Phillip Guo&lt;/a&gt; for tweeting about it and setting off the publicity storm, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/olgabot/prettyplotlib/graphs/contributors"&gt;all the contributors&lt;/a&gt; who took my measly code and made it great. I&amp;#8217;ve learned so much from the Python open source community and am so thankful that it is so easy to learn from others in this wonderful&amp;nbsp;environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to check out what I&amp;#8217;ve been working on instead, take a look at &lt;a href="https://github.com/YeoLab/flotilla"&gt;&lt;code&gt;flotilla&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the package I&amp;#8217;ve been working on with &lt;a href="https://github.com/mlovci"&gt;Michael Lovci&lt;/a&gt; for reproducible single-cell analysis. The package is still in its infancy (read: be prepared for bugs), and we are actively developing&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="python"></category><category term="visualization"></category><category term="prettyplotlib"></category><category term="seaborn"></category><category term="flotilla"></category></entry><entry><title>Migration to Github.io!</title><link href="/migration-to-github-io-English.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-25T08:58:51-07:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2014-09-25:migration-to-github-io-English.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I moved my blog from &lt;a href="http://www.tumblr.com/"&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt; for several&amp;nbsp;reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write posts in Markdown and IPython notebooks so figures, code, and LaTeX markup would show up&amp;nbsp;fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easily back up my posts. Before, I wrote my posts in &lt;a href="http://simplenote.com/"&gt;Simplenote&lt;/a&gt; and then copy-pasted to Tumblr, but I didn&amp;#8217;t like&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t use the re-blogging or following aspects of Tumblr much so I didn&amp;#8217;t see the advantages of that&amp;nbsp;network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awesome &lt;a href="http://www.pelicanthemes.com/"&gt;customizable themes&lt;/a&gt; using&amp;nbsp;Pelican.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few drawbacks, most notably, the comments from previous posts are still tied to the Tumblr website, because Tumblr doesn&amp;#8217;t use slugs (e.g. &amp;#8220;&lt;code&gt;migration-to-github-io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;) for its webpage names, instead it uses some random number generator for keeping track of posts, e.g &amp;#8220;post/72680703972&amp;#8221;. And because &lt;a href="https://disqus.com/"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; uses the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; from the post to map it back to its database, and I couldn&amp;#8217;t get the original mapping :( So comments for old posts will be back on&amp;nbsp;Tumblr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m excited for a new start with&amp;nbsp;blogging!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="github"></category><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>The second article</title><link href="/blog/2012/12/01/the-second-article/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-12-01T10:02:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Olga Botvinnik</name></author><id>tag:,2012-12-01:blog/2012/12/01/the-second-article/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;See below intra-site link examples in Markdown&amp;nbsp;format.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>